<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Articles to be enquired of, within the Archdeaconry of Midlesex, by the church-wardens &amp; swornemen in euery parish and presentment to be made thereof to the arch-deacon, with partciular [sic] answeres vnto euery article.</title>
            <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Middlesex.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10275.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2098</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23026083</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23026083</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26102</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26102)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1795:45)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Articles to be enquired of, within the Archdeaconry of Midlesex, by the church-wardens &amp; swornemen in euery parish and presentment to be made thereof to the arch-deacon, with partciular [sic] answeres vnto euery article.</title>
                  <author>Church of England. Archdeaconry of Middlesex.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[17] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Edw. Allde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B⁵.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
               <term>Visitations, Ecclesiastical --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26102:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26102:1"/>
            <p>ARTICLES <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To be enquired of, within the Archdeaconry of <hi>Midleſex, by the Church-wardens &amp; Sworne</hi>-men in euery Pariſh. <hi>And preſentment to be made thereof</hi> to the Arch-deacon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With particular Anſweres vnto</hi> euery Article</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by EDW: ALLDE. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="oath">
            <pb facs="tcp:26102:2"/>
            <head>The tenor of the Oath miniſtred to the <hi>Church-Wardens and Sworne-men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E ſhall ſweare, that all affections, fauour, hatred, hope of reward, or gaine, or feare of diſpleaſure or malice ſet aſide, you ſhall vpon due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Articles giuen you in charge preſent all and euery ſuch perſon, of, or within your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, as hath committed any offence or fault, or made any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault mentioned in any of theſe Articles, or which are vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mently ſuſpected, or otherwiſe defamed of any ſuch offence, fault or default, wherein you ſhall deale vprightly and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to equitie: neither of malice preſenting any contrary to Truth, nor of corrupt affection ſparing to preſent any, and ſo conceale the Truth, hauing in this action God before your eyes, with an earneſt zeale to maintaine truth, and to ſuppreſſe vice: So helpe you God and his faithfull promiſes in Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb facs="tcp:26102:2"/>
            <head>¶ Articles to be enquired of within the Archdeaconarie of Midleſex, for this preſent yeere of our Lord God. 1615.</head>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles concerning the Church.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether haue you in your ſeuerall Churches and Chappells the Booke of Conſtitutions or Canons Eccleſiaſticall, ready to be read by your Miniſter, according to his Maieſties pleaſure, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by his highnes authority vnder the great Seale of England.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether is there in your Church or Chappell, one parchment regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Booke, prouided for Chriſtnings, Marriages, and Burialls: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the ſame duely and exactly kept, according to the Conſtitutions in that caſe prouided, and a tranſcript thereof brought in yearely within one moneth after Eaſter, into my Lord Biſhops principall Regiſters office? and whether doth your Miniſter vpon euery Sunday reade the names of all ſuch as haue béene married, chriſtned, or buried the wéeke before?</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether haue you prouided the Booke of Common Prayer lately com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded by his Maieſties authority onely to be vſed, and the Booke of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, and two Pſalters: and whether haue you in your Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell a Font of ſtone, ſet vp in the antient vſuall place: a conuenient and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Communion table ſtanding vpon a frame, with a Carpet of ſilke, or ſome other decent ſtuffe: and a faire Linnen cloth to lay thereon at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion time: and whether is the ſame then placed in ſuch conuenient ſort within the Chancell or Church, as that the Miniſter may be beſt heard in his Prayer and adminiſtration, and that the greater number may commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate: and whether are the ten Commaundements ſet vp on the Eaſt end of your Church or Chappell, where the people may beſt ſée and reade them, and other ſentences of holy Scriptures written on the walls likewiſe for the ſame purpoſe?</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether haue you a conuenient ſeate for the Miniſter to reade ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice in, together with a comely Pulpit ſet vp in a conuenient place, with a decent cloth or Cuſhion for the ſame: a comely large Surples, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Communion Cup of Siluer, and a couer agreable for the ſame, with all
<pb facs="tcp:26102:3"/> other things and ornaments neceſſary for the celebration of diuine Seruice, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments, and a ſtrong cheſt for the almes of the poore, with thrée lockes and keyes, and another cheſt for the kéeping of the ornaments of the Church, and Regiſter Booke.</p>
               <p n="5">5 How many Bells are there at this preſent, hanging in the Belfrée of your pariſh Church, and how many haue there béene heretofore: whether any of your ſaid Bells haue béene taken downe and ſold, or made away: and what other Church goods are now wanting in your Church.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether are your Church or Chappells with the Chancells thereof, and your Parſonage or Vicarage houſe, and all other houſing thereto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing, in good reparations, and decently and comely kept, aſwell within as without: the ſeates well maintained, your Churchyards well fenced, and kept without abuſe, according to the 85. Canon: if not, then through whoſe default, and what defects are? All theſe things in theſe Articles to be prepared, according to the Canons vnder the title appertaining to Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles concerning the Clergie.</head>
               <p>VVHether hath your Miniſter read the Conſtitutions ſet foorth by his Maieſty, once euery yeare, vpon ſome Sundayes or Holidayes, in the afternoone, before diuine ſeruice: according as by the Canons he is bound?</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether doth your Miniſter vſe to pray for the Kings Maieſty, King <hi>Iames,</hi> and for the Quéenes Maieſty, Prince <hi>Charles, Fredericke</hi> Count <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine</hi> of the <hi>Rheine,</hi> with the Lady <hi>Elizabeth</hi> his Wife, giuing vnto his highneſſe ſuch ſtile and title of Supreme Gouernour of all cauſes, and ouer all perſons, as well Eccleſiaſticall as temporall, as by lawe are due vnto him, exhorting their Pariſhioners to yealde him obedience according to the ſame, and alſo in their ſaid Sermons, doe pray for all Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſticall perſons, according to the 55. Canon.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether is the preſcript forme of diuine ſeruice vſed by your Miniſter vpon Sundayes, Holydayes, Wedneſdayes, and Fridayes, according to the booke of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayer. And whether doth your Miniſter duly obſerue all the orders, rites, and ceremonies preſcribed in the ſaid booke of Common Prayer: as well in reading publike prayers, the Letany, as alſo in adminiſtring the Sacraments in ſuch manner and forme, wearing the Surples, as by the booke of Common Prayer by law now eſtabliſhed is inioyed.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether doth your Miniſter adminiſter the holy Communion ſo often, and at ſuch times as that euery Pariſhioner may receiue the ſame,
<pb facs="tcp:26102:3"/> at the leaſt thrice euery yeare, whereof one at Eaſter, as by the booke of Common Prayer is appointed. And whether doth your Miniſter receiue the ſame himſelfe on euery day that he adminiſtreth it to others, knéeling at the ſame, and adminiſtreth it to none but to ſuch as doe knéels at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing thereof, and vſe the words of the Inſtitution according to the Booke, at euery time that the bread and wine is receiued, in ſuch manner and forme as by the prouiſo of the 21. Canon is directed, or wherein is he faulty, and whether is warning giuen by him before hand for the Commuion, as the 22. Canon requireth.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether hath your Miniſter admitted any notorious offenders, or Schiſmatickes to the Communion: contrary to the 26. and 27. Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without ſatiſfaction by due courſe of law before enioyned them; or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected any from the Communion, who were not by publike preſentment, or other open ſcandall, infamous, and detected of ſome notorious crime by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fame publiſhed in the Pariſh.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether the Miniſter, together with the Churchwardens and Queſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, doe take diligent héed and care, that not onely all and euery of your owne Pariſhioners doe receiue thrice in euery yeare, as aforeſaid: but alſo that no ſtrangers of any other Pariſh doe forſake their owne Miniſter and Pariſh, to receiue with you, contrary to the 28. Canon.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Whether doth your Miniſter vſe to ſigne the Children with the ſigne of the Croſſe when they are baptized, according to the booke of Common Prayer, and the 30. Canon: and whether he hath deferred, or wilfully refoled to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize any infant in his Pariſh being in danger, hauing béene onely infor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the weakneſſe thereof, and whether the childe hath died by him default with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out baptiſme, contrary to the 68. and 69. Canons.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether is your Miniſter continually reſident with you vpon his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefice: or for how long time hath he béene abſent, and where is he reſident for the moſt part, and what other be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Whether doth ydl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Miniſter being a Preacher; preach vſually accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the conſtitutions, eyther in his owne thee with your once euery ſunday or elſe in ſome other Church or Chappell néere adioyning, where no Preacher is, according to the 45. Canon, or how hath he bene negligent in that behalfe.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether is your Miniſter a Preacher allowed if yea, then by whome: if no, whether doth he procure Sermons to be preached among you once in euery moneth at the leaſt, by ſuch as are lawfully licenſed, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the 46. Canon, or doth contribute toward a licenſed Preacher, if his liuing will beare it.</p>
               <p n="11">11 Whether hath your Miniſter another benefice: and whether doth
<pb facs="tcp:26102:4"/> he ſupply his abſence by a Curate, that is ſufficiently licenſed to preach in that cure of his, whereon he himſelfe is not reſident: or otherwiſe in caſe he doe not finde a preaching Miniſter there, by reaſon of the ſmalneſſe thereof, whether doth he preach at both his benefices vſually himſelfe, according to the 47. Canon?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether is your Preacher or Curate licenſed to preach or ſerue the Cure, by the Biſhop of this Dioces, or by any other, and by whom: whether doth your Miniſter or Curate ſerue more cures then one, contrary to the 48. Canon. If yea, then what other cure doth he alſo ſerue?</p>
               <p n="13">13 If your Miniſter be not licenſed to preach as aforeſaid, whether doth he reade Homilies, or rather take vpon him to expound the Scriptures either in his owne cure or elſe where contrary to the 49. Canon: If yea, then you are to preſent him; and ſpot me the place where he ſo hath preached.</p>
               <p n="14">14 Whether hath any perſon béen admitted to preach within your Church or Chappell, but ſuch as you haue well knowne to be ſufficiently licenſed: whome haue you ſo admitted? you ſhall preſent their names, and how often haue any ſuch béene admitted to preach, and by whoſe procurement: and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue you cauſed euery ſtrange Preacher, licenſed or not licenſed, to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe his name, together with the day when he preached, according to the 50. and 51. Canons: and if he were licenſed, then by whom he was licenſed: And whether haue they or any other preached in your Church not being ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berly and decently apparrelled according to the 47. Canon.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Whether doth your Lecturer and Preacher reade diuine Seruice, and adminiſter the Sacraments in his owne perſon twice euery yeare, obſeruing all the Ceremonies in the booke of Common Prayer eſtabliſhed according to the 56. Canon.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether doth your Miniſter weare the Surples whileſt he is ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the publike prayers, and adminiſtring the Sacraments: And if he be any Graduate, whether then doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we are vpon his Surples, during the times aforeſaid, ſuch a hood, as by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ders of his Vniuerſitie is agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his degrée, according to then 58. Canon.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether doth your Miniſter euery Sunday and Holyday, before E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening Prayer, for halfe an houre or more, examine and inſtruct the youth, and ignorant perſons of his Pariſh, in the ten Commandements the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of beliefe, and the Lords Prayer, as alſo in the Catechiſme laſt ſet forth in the booke of Common prayer, whereby the chidren of the Pariſh may be prepared for confirmation, according to the 90. Canon.</p>
               <p n="18">18 Whether hath your Miniſter without licenſe from the Archbiſhop, the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or his Chancelor, or without Lycence vnder the ſeale of office of the Archdeacon or his Officiall, ſolemnized mariage betwixt any
<pb facs="tcp:26102:4"/> parties, the Banes not being three ſeuerall Sundayes or Holly-dayes firſt publiſhed in time of diuine ſeruice, in the ſeuerall Churches or Chappels of their ſeuerall abode, according to the booke of common Prayer, And the 62. Canon: and that alſo betwixt the houres of eight and twelue in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, contrary to the 102. Canon. And whether hath your miniſter in the times prohibited marryed, any without ſuch Licence, notwithſtanding the banes haue bene aſked, as you doe knowe, beléeue, or haue heard ſay.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whether hath your Miniſter, ſince the laſt Canons publiſhed, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnized any marryage betwixt any perſons, being vnder the age of 21. yéeres, alchough the Banes be thrice asked, before ſuch time as the parents haue made knowne vnto him their conſent thereunto, contrary to the 99. and 100. Canons: and whether hath he married any of another Diocoſſe, and who are they, and by what authoritie, and when.</p>
               <p n="20">20 Whether doth your Miniſter vpon Sundayes at morning prayer, declare vnto the Pariſhioners what holy dayes and faſting dayes are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be kept the wéeke following, according to the 64. Canon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they may be put in minde to prepare themſelues accordingly, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to the Church to publike prayer, as by law they are bound.</p>
               <p n="21">21 Whether doth your Miniſter in the Rogation dayes, vſe the peram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation of the circuit of the pariſh appointed by law, and in the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ambulation, moue the people to giue thankes to God for his benefits vſing ſuch Pſalmes, Prayers, Homilies, as are to that end ſet forth.</p>
               <p n="22">22 Whether doth any man (being neither Miniſter nor Deacon) reade Common-prayer openly in your Church or Chappell, or adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme, or ſolemnize Matrimonie, or take vpon him to practiſe any other miniſteriall dutie in the Church, that is preſcribed to be executed particularly by ſuch, as are either Miniſters, or Deacons, and what is his name that ſo doth.</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whether doth your Miniſter euery ſixe moneths denounce in his pariſh, all ſuch of his pariſh, as doe perſeuer in the ſentence of excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, not ſéeking to be abſolued: and whether hath he admitted any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon excommunicate, into the Church, without a Certificate of his abſolution from the Ordinarie or other competent Iudge, vnder his ſeale, according to the Canons.</p>
               <p n="24">24 Whether doth your Miniſter being a Preacher, endeuour and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour diligently with mildenes and temperance to conferre with, and thereby to reclaime the Popiſh Recuſants in his pariſh from their errours, if there be any ſuch there being: and whether is he painefull in viſitation of the ſicke, according to the booke of Common-prayer, and the Canons in that caſe prouided.</p>
               <p n="25">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26102:5"/>25 Whether is your Parſon, Vicar, Lecturer, or Curate too much fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent or ouer conuerſant with, or a fauourer or Recuſants, whereby he may be ſuſpected not to be ſincere in Religion.</p>
               <p n="26">26 Whether hath your Miniſter, or any other, taking vpon him the place of a Miniſter, preached, baptized children (vnleſſe in caſe of neceſſitie) ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized marriage, churched any woman, or miniſtred the holy Communion in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny priuate houſe or houſes: if yea, then where, whome, and how often hath he ſo offended in any of the premiſes.</p>
               <p n="27">27 Whether hath your Miniſter taken vpon him to appoint any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like or priuate faſts or propheſſes, not approoued and eſtabliſhed by lawe or publike authority: or hath he attempted vpon any pretence either of poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by faſting and prayer to caſt out deuills, contrary vnto the 72. Canon.</p>
               <p n="28">28 Whether hath your Miniſter, or any other perſon or perſons within your Pariſh vſed to méete in any priuate houſe or other place, and to hold pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate conuenticles, contrary to the 73. Canon: if yea, then you ſhall preſent them all and euery one of them.</p>
               <p n="29">29 Whether doth your Miniſter vſe ſuch decencie and comelineſſe in his apparrell, as by the 74. conſtitution is enioyned him, as well at home as when he goeth abroad.</p>
               <p n="30">30 Whether doe you know in your Pariſh, any that hauing heretofore taken vpon him or them, the order of Prieſt-hood or of a Deacon, hath ſince relinquiſhed the ſame, and betaken himſelfe to the courſe of his life, a Lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, neglecting his vocation: if yea, then you ſhall preſent his name and the place of his abode.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Whether is your Miniſter noted or defamed to haue obtained his Benefice by Symony, or reputed to be an incontinent perſon, or doth kéepe any man or woman in his houſe, that are ſuſpected either to be of euill religion, or bad life, himſelfe to be a common drunkard, or to be a common hunter of Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernes, Alchouſes, or other ſuſpected places, a common gameſter or player at dice, or other vnlawfull games, a common ſwearer, or notorious perſon, or faulty in any other crime puniſhable by Eccleſiaſticall cenſures, whereby he is offenſiue and ſcandalous to his function or miniſtery.</p>
               <p n="32">32 Whether doth your Miniſter vſe the forme of thankeſgiuing to wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men after their childbirth, and whether hath he admitted any thereunto that was begotten with childe in adultery or fornication, without licenſe of his Ordinary, and whether haue any married wiues refuſed to come to Church, according to the booke of Common Prayer, to giue God thankes after childe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birth: if any be faulty herein, you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Whether doth your Miniſter baptize any children in any Baſon, or other veſſells, then in the ordinary Font being placed in the Church, according
<pb facs="tcp:26102:5"/> to the 81. Canon or doth vſe to put any baſon into it.</p>
               <p n="34">34 Whether in the time of diuine Seruice, and of euer part thereof, all due reuerence is vſed: no man then couering his head, all manner of perſons knéeling when Prayers are read, and ſtanding vp at the ſaying of the Beliefe, according to the order preſcribed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles concerning Schoolemaſters.</head>
               <p>VVHether the Schoolemaſter or Schoolemaſters within your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, openly or priuately, in any Noble or Gentlemans houſe, or in any other place, be of good and ſincere Religion life and conuerſation, &amp; be diligent in the teaching and bringing vp of youth: and whether they haue béene examined, allowed and licenſed for Schoole-maſters, by the Ordinarie in that behalfe: and how many ſeuerall Schoole-maſters haue you, and what be their names.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether your Schoole-maſter, or Schoole-maſters doe themſelues receiue the holy Communion as often as they ought to doe: and whether doe all their Schollers, which be of age ſufficient, and or capacitie, by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to receiue the Lords Supper, come to the Communion either in your Church, or where their Parents dwell, once euery yeere, and be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to feare Common Prayer.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether the Schoole-maſter, or Schoole maſters, either priuate or publike, doe teach their Schollers the Catechiſme authorized by publike authoritie, at the leaſt once euery wéeke, and doe inſtruct &amp; examine them in the ſame, or doe teach any other Catechiſme, and what Catechiſme it is that they doe teach.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether your Schoole-maſter, or Schoole-maſters, or any of them be knowne or ſuſpected to reade vnto their Schollers priuately, any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Bookes, or priuately to inſtruct them in their young yéeres, either in Popery, ſuperſtition, diſobedience, or contempt to his Maieſtie, and his Lawes Eccleſiaſticall by publike authoritie allowed.</p>
               <p n="5">5 What recuſant Papiſts are there in your Pariſh, and whether doe they, or any of them kéepe any Schoole maſter in their houſe, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to Church to heare Diuine Seruice, and receiue the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: what is his name, and how long hath he taught.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether the Schoole-maſter, or Schoole-maſters within your Pariſh, doe teach his or their Srhollers any other Grammer, then that which is called the Kings Grammer, ſet forth by the authoritie of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, teaching the preſcript forme thereof, whereby the Schollers may perfectly vnderſtand their Grammer rules and conſtructions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:26102:6"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Pariſhioners, Eccleſiaſticall Officers and others of the Laytie.</head>
               <p n="1">1 WHether is there any within your Pariſh, that hath, or doth impugne the Kings Maieſties ſupremacie and authoritie in cauſes Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall, or doe any way, or in any part impeach the ſame, being reſtored to the Crowne by the lawes of this Realme eſtabliſhed on that behalfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Whether is there any in your pariſh that denieth the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land by law eſtabliſhed vnder the Kings moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Maieſtie to be a true &amp; Apoſtolicall Church, teaching &amp; maintaining the doctrine of the Apoſtles.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Whether is there any in your Pariſh, that doth impugne any of the Articles of Religion agréed vpon in <hi>An.</hi> 1562. &amp; eſtabliſhed in the Church of England.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Whether is there any in your Pariſh that doe impugne or ſpeake a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the rites and ceremonies eſtabliſhed in the Church of England, or the lawfull vſe of them: you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Whether are there any in your Pariſh that doe impugne the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of the Church of England, vnder the Kings moſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Archdeacons, and the reſt that beare office in the ſame, affirming that he ſame is Antichriſtian, or repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the word of God.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Whether is there any in your pariſh that impugne the forme of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration and ordayning of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, affirming that the ſame is repugnant to the word of God, or that they, who are ſo ordered in the ſame forme, are not lawfully made.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Whether is there any in your pariſh that doth hold or frequent any conuenticles, or priuate méetings, and there doe conferre or agrée vpon any priuate orders, other then ſuch as are by the Canons ſet forth by publike authority, to be by them or any other in Church gouernment obſerued.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Whether any perſons haue lurked or tipled in Tauerns or Ale hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes on Sundaies, or other Holy dayes, or vſed his, or their manuall craft, trade, or myſterie, or any bodylie labour, or kéept their ſhops open vpon the ſaide dayes, or any of them, eſpecially in the time of diuine ſeruice?</p>
               <p n="9">9 Whether are there any in your pariſh that doe, or haue prophaned (ſince his Maieſties laſt generall pardon) the Lords day, called Sunday, or other Holy-day, contrary to the orders of the Church of England, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in that behalfe?</p>
               <p n="10">10 Whether hath any perſon in your pariſh quarrelled, ſtricken, or vſed any violence vnto, or with your Miniſter, or any other in the Church or Church yard, or vſed himſelfe diſorderly in the Church, by filthie and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane talke, or any other rude and immodeſt behauiour?</p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26102:6"/>11 Whether is that due reuerence and humble ſubmiſſion, vſed within your Church or Chappel in the time of diuine Seruice, as by the eightéenth Conſtitution is preſcribed? and whether each one in the Church or Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, doe apply and order himſelfe there in the time of diuine Seruice, as by the latter part of the ſame Conſtitution is moſt commendably enioyned?</p>
               <p n="12">12 Whether the Church-wardens and Queſt-men doe euery Sunday and Holy-day diligently ſearch who abſenteth himſelfe, or her ſelfe from Church? and whether doe they ſuffer any to abide in the Church-porch, or Church-yard, in the time of Common prayer or Sermon?</p>
               <p n="13">13 Whether the Church-wardens doe prouide againſt euery Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, with the aduice of the Miniſter, a ſufficient quantitie of fine white bread, and of good &amp; wholſome wine, for the number of the Communicants that ſhall receiue, &amp; that to be brought in a cleane and ſwéete ſtanding Pot of Pewter, or other pure Mettall?</p>
               <p n="14">14 Whether haue any in your pariſh béene God fathers or God-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to their owne children? Or whether your Miniſter, or any God-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers or God-mothers haue vſed, or doe vſe any other forme, anſwere, or ſpéech in Baptiſme, then is in the Booke of Common prayer appoynted? Or whether any which haue not Communicated, be admitted to be God-fathers, or God-mothers, contrarie to the 29. Canone.</p>
               <p n="15">15 Whether is there any in your pariſh that doe refuſe to haue their children baptized, or themſelues to receiue the Communion at the hands of your Miniſter, becauſe he is no Preacher? you ſhall preſent their names. And if your Miniſter, ſithence the publiſhing of the ſaid Booke of Canons, haue receiued any ſuch perſons (being not of his owne Cure) to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, or baptized any of their children, you ſhall likewiſe preſent him.</p>
               <p n="16">16 Whether doe all Fathers, Mothers, Maſters, and Miſtreſſes, cauſe their Children, Seruants, and Apprentiſes, to come to the Catechiſme vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sundayes and Holy-dayes before euening prayer, to heare and to be inſtructed and taught therein? and thoſe that doe not their duties here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, you ſhall preſent their names.</p>
               <p n="17">17 Whether haue you, or your Predeceſſors Church-wardens there ſuffered, ſince the laſt pardon, any Playes, Feaſts, Banquets, Church-ales, Drinkings, or any other prophane vſages to be kept in your Church, Chappels, or Church, yard, or Bels to be rung ſuperſtitiouſly vpon Holy-dayes, or Eues, abrogated by the Booke of Common Prayer, contrarie to the 68. Canon?</p>
               <p n="18">18 How many Inhabitants within your Pariſh, Men, or Women, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the age of ſixtéene yéeres, doe refuſe to frequent diuine ſeruice, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by publike authoritie of this Realme, or to receiue the holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb facs="tcp:26102:7"/> or are negligent therein? what be their names, and of what degrée, ſtate, or trade of life are they? you are to preſent them all of each ſort.</p>
               <p n="19">19 Whether doe any of the Inhabitants within your ſaide Pariſh en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine within their houſe any ſoiourners, ledgers, or any common reſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and gueſts, who refuſe to frequent diuine Seruice, or receiue the holy Communion, as aforeſaid? what be their names, and of what qualitie or condition are they?</p>
               <p n="20">20 whether any of the ſaid Popiſh Recuſants be of inſolent behauiour, not without publike offence, or doe boldly buſie themſelues in ſeducing, or withdrawing others, either abroad or in their owne families, by inſtructing their children in Popiſh religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or by refuſing to entertaine any, eſpecially in place of greateſt ſeruice or truſt, but ſuch as concur with them in opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Religion: and what be their names that ſo doe?</p>
               <p n="21">21 How long the ſaid Popiſh Recuſants haue obſtinately abſtained ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from diuine Seruice, or from the Communion, as is aforeſayd, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of any long time, or onely ſince his Maieſties raigne, and how long?</p>
               <p n="22">22 What perſons aforeſaid within your Pariſh, either for the offence aforeſaid, or for any other contumacie or crime, doe remaine excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? what be their names? and for what cauſe? and how long haue they ſo ſtood excommunicated?</p>
               <p n="23">23 Whether were you the Church wardens and Queſt-men choſen by the conſent of the Miniſter and Pariſhioners, in Eaſter wéeke, according vnto the 89. and 90. Canon. And whether haue the Church-wardens be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you giuen vp a iuſt account for their time, and deliuered to you their ſucceſſors, whatſoeuer money or other thing of right belonging to the Church, which was in their hands: according to the 89. Canon.</p>
               <p n="24">24 Whether doe all perſons aboue the age of ſixetéene yoores, vſually reſort to heare diuine Seruice vpon Sundaies and Holy-daies approoued? and whether hath each one of your Pariſhioners (being aboue the age of ſixtéene yéeres, as aforeſaid) receiued the holy Communion thrice this laſt yéere, chiefely once at Eaſter, in your Pariſh Church knéeling? If no, then you ſhall preſent their name which haue not ſo done.</p>
               <p n="25">25 Whether haue you a fit Pariſh Clarke, aged twentie yéeres at the leaſt, of honeſt conuerſation, and ſufficient for reading and writing? and whether he be paide his wages without fraude, according to the moſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cuſtome of your Pariſh? if not, then by whom is he ſo defrauded and denyed? and whether he be choſen by the Parſon or Vicar, or by whom, according to the 91. Canon?</p>
               <p n="26">26 Whether haue any in your Pariſh béene marryed within the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited degrées forbidden by the law, and expreſſed in a certaine Table pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb facs="tcp:26102:7"/> by authority in <hi>Anno.</hi> 1563. If yea, then you ſhall preſent their names? and whether haue you the ſaide Table publikely ſet vp in your Church, and faſtned to ſome conuenient place?</p>
               <p n="27">27 Whether doth any heretofore diuorced, or married and not diuor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, kéepe company at bed and boord as man and wife, with any other man or woman, then with the perſon that he or ſhe was married vnto? and what be their names? If the parties now ſo liuing together, ſay that they be marryed, when and where were they marryed? and how long haue they ſo continued together?</p>
               <p n="28">28 Whether haue you in your Pariſh to your knowledge, or by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon fame and report, any which haue committed Adultery, Fornication, or Inceſt, or any Bawdes, harborers, or receiuers of ſuch perſons, or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely ſuſpected thereof, which haue not béene publikely puniſhed to your knowledge? if yea, then with whome? And whether are there any which are by common fame and report reputed and taken to be common Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kards, Blaſphemers of Gods holy Name, common and vſuall ſwearers, filthy ſpeakers, raylers, ſowers of diſcord among their Neighbours, or ſpeakers againſt Miniſters marriages: Vſurers, contrarie to the Statute made in the ſeauen and thirtieth yéere of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, Symonicall perſons, fighters, brawlers, or quarrellers in Church or Church-yard? you ſhall not faile to preſent their names.</p>
               <p n="29">29 Whether haue any in your Pariſh receiued or harboured any wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man gotten with childe out of wedlock, and ſuffered them againe to depart without pennance firſt inflicted vpon them by their Ordinarie? you ſhall truly preſent as well the partie harbouring as harboured, and who is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to haue committed incontinencie with her.</p>
               <p n="30">30 Whether any perſon or perſons ſuſpected or detected heretofore of incontinencie, and therefore departing out of your Pariſh for a ſeaſon, is now returned againe? or in what place elſe is he or ſhe now abiding to your knowledge, or as you haue heard? you ſhall not faile to preſent the whole truth in that behalfe.</p>
               <p n="31">31 Whether there be any perſon or perſons Eccleſiaſticall or Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall within your Pariſh, or elſewhere within the Dioces, that haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned and kept in their cuſtodie, or that reade, ſell, vtter, diſperſe, carrie, or deliuer to others any Engliſh or Latine Bookes, or Libels, ſet foorth or printed, either on this ſide or beyond the Seas, by Papiſts or Sectaries a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Kings Supremacie in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall; or tending to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, Puritaniſme, or any other Sect, Errour, or Hereſie, againſt true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and Catholike doctrine, now publikely profeſſed in this Church, or the gouernment or diſcipline of the Church of England, now within this
<pb facs="tcp:26102:8"/> Realme receiued and eſtabliſhed by common authoritie, that you know or haue heard of, what their names and ſir names are?</p>
               <p n="32">32 Whether there be any in your Pariſh who are knowne or ſuſpected to conceale, or kéepe hidden in their houſes any Maſſe Bookes, Porteſſes, Breuiaries, or other Bookes of Popery or ſuperſtition: or any Challices, Copes, Veſtments, Albes, or other ornaments of ſuperſtition, vncancelled, or vndefaced, which is to be coniectured that they doe kéepe for a day, as they call it.</p>
               <p n="33">33 Whether any of your Pariſhioners, hauing a Preacher to their Parſon, Vicar, or Curate, doe abſent themſelues from his Sermons, and reſort to any other place to heare other Preachers.</p>
               <p n="34">34 Whether there be any Inne-kéepers, Alewiues, Victuallers, or Tiplers, that ſuffer or doe admit any perſon, or perſons in their houſes, to eate, drinke, or play at Dice, Cards, Tables, Bowles, or ſuch like games, in the time of Common prayer or Sermon, on Sundaies or Holy-daies: Or any Butchers, or other, that commonly vſe to ſell meate or other things in the time of Common prayer, Preaching, or reading of Homilies? and whether in any Fayres, or common Markets, falling vpon Sundaies, there be ſhewing of any wares before morning prayer be done? And whether any Markets or ſelling of wares be vſed, or ſuffered in any Church-yards on the Sabbath day by common pack-men and Pedlers go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about, or any Butchers?</p>
               <p n="35">35 Whether hath your Miniſter, or any of the pariſh, without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or priuitie of the Ordinarie, cauſed any to doe penance, or to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed either openly or otherwiſe, by any Veſtrie meetings, or taken mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for any crime puniſhable by the Eccleſiaſticall lawes onely, and what be the names of the parties that haue béene ſo puniſhed, and in what manner?</p>
               <p n="36">36 Whether there be any in your pariſh who will come to heare the Sermon, but will not come to the publike prayer, appointed by the Booke of common prayer, making a ſchiſme or diuiſion (as it were) betwéene the vſe of publike prayer and preaching? and whether there be any who being preſent at publike prayer, doe not deuoutly and humbly knéele vpon their knées, at ſuch times as by the Booke of common prayer they are appointed: to wit, when they make a generall confeſſion of their ſinnes: when all Prayers and Collects are read: in the time of the Letanie: when the ten Commandements are read: &amp; at the receiuing of the holy Communion, &amp;c. And what be their names that haue at any time ſhewed themſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutifull and vnreuerent in that behalfe?</p>
               <p n="37">37 Whether there be any married women, or others within your pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,
<pb facs="tcp:26102:8"/> which after childe-birth refuſe, contemne, or neglect, to come to the Church to giue God thanks for their ſafe deliuerie, &amp; to haue the prayers publikely appointed in that behalfe by the Booke of common prayer?</p>
               <p n="38">38 Whether any within your pariſh doe reſort into Barnes, Fields, Woods, priuate houſes, to any extraordinary expoſition of Scriptures, or conferences together, or that be drawers or perſwaders of others to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch ſchiſmaticall conuenticle.</p>
               <p n="39">39 Whether any doe kéepe their children vnbaptized longer then is conuenient, vnleſſe that it be for the ſickneſſe of the childe, or other vrgent occaſion? And whether any doe carry their childe or children from the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh they are borne in, to other pariſhes to be baptized, and ſo refuſe their owne pariſh, and to what other pariſh? or doe bring ſtrange Miniſters into their own houſes to baptize their children priuately, according to their owne fantaſies?</p>
               <p n="40">40 <hi>Item,</hi> (Setting downe the full ſumme of the Communicants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in your Pariſh) you ſhall preſent euery one who hath béene defectiue at this feaſt of Eaſter laſt paſt, in receiuing the holy Communion vpon neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, contempt, or any other pretence and excuſe.</p>
               <p n="41">41 Whether doe you know of any other matter of Eccleſiaſticall cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance worthy the preſentment, in your iudgement, heretofore in theſe Articles not expreſſed, and which is fit to be reformed in Eccleſiaſticall cenſure? If you doe, you ſhall likewiſe preſent the ſame by vertue of your oathes.</p>
               <p n="42">42 Whether hath your Miniſter kept any Excommunication in his cuſtodie vnpubliſhed againſt any of his Pariſhioners, aboue the ſpace of xx. dayes next after the receit thereof, without ſome lawfull certificat of the abſolution of any ſuch excommunicate perſon, or of ſome lawfull war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for the ſtay of the ſame Excommunication.</p>
               <p n="43">43 Whether hath your Miniſter admitted any excommunicate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to the holy Communion before he hath receiued a certificat of the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the ſame partie: And whether haue you permitted any excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate perſon either of your owne pariſh or of any other pariſh, to heare diuine Seruice in your pariſh Church, ſince the time you looke vpon you the office of Church wardens within your ſaide pariſh? If yea, ſet downe the names of the ſame parties.</p>
               <p n="44">44 Whether hath your Miniſter abſolued any excommunicate perſon or perſons of your pariſh, or of any other pariſh within the Archdeaconey of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> within the ſpace of a yéere laſt paſt, without a ſpeciall warrant in writing vnder the hands of the Iudge and Regiſter of this Court, or of one of them? If yea, what are the names of ſuch perſon or perſons which he hath ſo abſolued.</p>
               <p n="45">
                  <pb facs="tcp:26102:9"/>45 Whether hath your Miniſter, your ſelues, or your predeceſſors Church-wardens of your pariſh for the yeere laſt paſt, preſented any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons of your ſaid pariſh to the Chancellor of the reuerend Father in God, the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London</hi> (ſauing in the Viſitation of the ſayd Lord Biſhop,) And whether hath your Miniſter, yourſelues, or your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors Church-wardens of your ſaid pariſh, for the yéer laſt paſt, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted any perſon or perſons to the Commiſſarie of the ſaid reuerend Father in God? If yea, what are the names of ſuch perſon or perſons which you or they haue ſo preſented, and for what cauſe did you or they preſent any ſuch perſon or perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <head>Articles to be inquired of, by the Miniſter, Church-wardens, &amp; Sworne-men of euery Pariſh within the Archdeaconrie of <hi>Midleſex,</hi> according to the ſpeciall direction of certaine letters heretofore ſent to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> from the right Honourable the Lords of the Priuie Counſell.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN primis,</hi> Whether there be any in your Pariſh, either Pariſhioners, Soiourners, or ſuch as be late come out of other Countries into your Pariſh, which do refuſe to come to diuine Seruice to the Pariſh Church, or elſewhere: and what be their names, and ſir-names, and how long they haue refuſed ſo to doe.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Item,</hi> How many of their wiues and children aboue the age of ſixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téene yéeres, ſeruants and other ſoiourners, abiding in their houſes, doe likewiſe refuſe ſo to doe: and what be their names and ſir-names, and how long they haue refuſed ſo to doe?</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether there be any in your Pariſh, which be ſuſpected to haue béene reconciled to the Popiſh Religion, or to haue béene abſolued, or any that procured or councelled any thereunto: and what be their names and ſir-names.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether there be any in your Pariſh which be ſuſpected to be Maſſing Prieſts, Reconcilers, Ieſuits, Seminaries, or other perſons, which haue receiued any orders or authoritie from the Romiſh Church, to vſe the like: and what be their names and ſir-names.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Item,</hi> Whether there be any Schoole-maſters within your Pariſh, which doe not bring vp their youth in the Religion now profeſſed, or be not themſelues diligent in repayring to diuine Seruice, or bringing their Scholers to it?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:26102:9"/>
               <head>Articles concerning Pariſhioners.</head>
               <p>IN euery Pariſh where any manner of perſon dwelleth or ſoiourneth, which refuſeth to goe to ſome Church to heare diuine Seruice: the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and Church-wardens of that Pariſh are commanded euery Moneth from henceforth, to goe to euery ſuch perſon with two or thrée honeſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and before thoſe witneſſes, to require euery ſuch perſon to repayre to the Church to heare Diuine Seruice. And the ſaide Miniſter and Church-wardens are commanded to ſend a Certificat in writing ſigned with the hands, marks, and ſeales of the ſayde Miniſter, Church-war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and witneſſes, to their Archdeacon, alwaies on the tenth day before Midſummer day: on the tenth day before Michaelmas day: on the tenth day before Chriſtmas day: and on the tenth day before our Lady day in Lent. So as returne of ſuch certificat may be made in time to the <hi>Cuſtos rotulorum</hi> at euery Seſſions next enſuing thoſe Feaſts, teſtifying as well the manner and time of their admoniſhments of ſuch Recuſants whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they be, as their anſwers. And when and whither they went to Church euery Moneth, after ſuch admonition giuen to them, as aforeſaid. Or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſuch perſon hath wilfully withdrawn himſelfe from taking or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding ſuch admonition: and alſo declaring the names, ſirnames, and abiding places of euery one that ſhall offend in any part or clauſe of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue written Articles. This euery Miniſter and Church-warden is ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie charged to ſhew his diligence in, and effectually to doe, as they and euery of them ſhall and will anſwere to the contrarie, at their perils.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſhall bring your Preſentment into the Regiſtrie of the Arcdeaconrie of <hi>Midleſex,</hi> ten dayes before euery quarter, ſpecifying the proper &amp; ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name, title, and addition of euery perſon preſented, and how many mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths they haue refuſed to come to diuine Seruice to their Pariſh Church, or elſewhere, before the day of making your Preſentment. And at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerie of your ſaid Preſentment you ſhal likewiſe ſet downe, in the latter end thereof, the names of ſuch as haue beene buryed within your ſayde Pariſh for the ſpace of a quarter of a yeere laſt paſt before the date of your ſaid Bill, being Men, Maides, or Widdowes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
